So maternity insurance.  Maternity
insurance is
not an inbuilt feature in your health insurance policy by default.
In most of the policies.  If you are
planning a baby or are newly married
and want your maternity to be covered, then
this video is very important for you.
Because many times it
seems whether one should take maternity cover or
not?  What is its benefit?
How much coverage is available?
How much does his premium go for?  So these are many questions that arise
before taking maternity cover.  And yes, there
is a cooling off period for taking maternity cover.  If you take the policy today,
you will not get immediate maternity coverage.
Plan options with waiting periods ranging from 9 months to 2 years are
available for you to choose from.  So we will
talk in detail whether
you should actually take a maternity plan or not.
[Music]
So what is maternity cover?  Maternity
cover is that which covers your delivery
expenses and delivery related expenses
which includes delivery cost.  Whether
it is normal or cesarean, it is covered.
Even if you are undergoing IVF procedures,
that is also covered.
Surrogacy and adoption are
all benefits covered in many policies.  So this is
called complete parenthood that the parenthood
benefit is included in your policy.
Along with this, newborn baby expenses i.e.
expenses of the child after delivery,
any hospitalization of the child,
vaccination expenses, all these are
covered in your maternity plus.  And these come
with some waiting periods.  Next, we will
look at some examples to see what the
waiting periods and
premiums are.  So, waiting period
means that if you have taken the policy today and
you immediately say that you want to take
maternity claim, then that is
not possible.  This means that you have to take the maternity policy
before conception.  To be
taken before conceiving.  If you take it after conceiving,
your maternity and newborn baby
expenses will not be covered.  So here the
minimum waiting period is
9 months.  That too is a policy of Neevapar
which has a waiting period of nine months and in
other plans, two years
waiting period options are available.  Two
years and three years plans are also available.
But mainly two years plans are
easily available in the market.  And
for this you have to pay additional premium.
Meaning a rider has to be added.  You have to tell
that you want to take maternity benefit.
You will have to show your interest.
Only then will the insurance company give you maternity
plans.  So, by default maternity is covered
in many plans, that is, there are only a few plans in
which it is covered by default.  Rest
you have to take add ons.  So don't assume
that if I
take health insurance, I will also get maternity cover.
For that a separate rider has to be taken.
So how much cover do you get?  Now this
is also a very interesting thing.  Here
people think that if I have taken a policy of Rs 10 lakh
or Rs 20 lakh, then my
maternity claim will also be of that much.  No.
You know that if you are getting delivery done in Tier One Zone
in cities like Delhi, Mumbai,
then the cost can be Rs 3 lakh, Rs 4 lakh or even more than that.
So do not
assume that in a policy of Rs 10 lakh, they will definitely give Rs
2-3 lakh, otherwise they will not
give that.  There is a fixed benefit.  You will
get the same sum assured as you have taken for maternity.  We will understand further with an example.
Now let us understand it with an example.  So
here I have taken two adults age 35 and
31 and have calculated the premium on that.  So
maternity is just a separate plan, we
cannot take only maternity plan.  You will have to
take maternity add-on along with your health insurance
or you will have to take health insurance only.  There
is no plan available for maternity coverage only.  As we will talk about, we have taken a
policy for two adults.  Ages are 35 and
31.  Here I have considered three plans.
Like Neevapa Aspire Plan.
ICIC LBA has Elevate plan and HDFCR has
Optima Secure plan which are offering maternity.
So it is inbuilt in Neevapa Aspire.
You do not have to take any rider separately.  You have to
choose the fast forward option.
I will tell you what it is now.
In ICIC LBA Elevate you have to choose the rider.
Which is newborn baby expenses?
It has a different rider.  Vaccination is different
and maternity is different.  All three are different
riders.
You will have to choose all three riders - Maternity, Newborn and Vaccination -
if you want to cover these things.
And HDFC Ergo Optima Secure also has a
paternity rider for which additional premium has to be
paid.  In this you can get maternity cover.
Waiting Periods The waiting period for Neevapire
is 9 months.  Meaning, if you
take the policy today and delivery takes place after 9 months, then
it is covered in the policy.  And
if you are not using it then it is carried
forward.  Because there is a booster plus in it
that suppose you do not use that limit
in that year, it will be carried forward to the next year.  It will
go up to a maximum of 10 times.
Whatever your maternity limit is, it will increase
and go up to 10 times.  Similarly,
if you look at ICICI Low LMA Elevate Plan, there is a
fixed benefit which is 10% of sum
assured up to a maximum of ₹1 lakh for maternity and the
waiting period is 2 years.  This means that
you will be covered for maternity only after 2 years.  2
years means you paid the premium today,
paid the premium next year, and paid the premium the year after that.
You can get maternity benefits covered after paying three premiums.  An
add-on is also available in which
you can reduce the maternity waiting period to one
year.  So, that option is also available.
You can choose that if you want to reduce.
Here we will talk about two years.
HDFCR is also available in Optima Secure
with a waiting period of two years
and maternity benefit options available are Rs
50,000, 1 lakh, 1.5 lakh and 2 lakh.  Now let's talk
about Neevapa Aspire Plan.  So
here two options are available: Fast Forward and Without Fast
Forward.
You do not have to take any add-on for maternity.  And
I told you it will be carried forward.  Let us
understand with an example.
Suppose we took a cover of ₹1 lax.  We
took 10 in all.  So that will be an Apple to Apple
comparison.  For a cover of ₹1 lax,
your premium is ₹18,902
for one year.  For 2 years it is Rs 36389 and
you take a 3 year policy upfront where
you get multi tenure discount.  The
premium is Rs 52458.  Now there is an option
available in it called Fast Forward.  This means you
can get three years of cover together on Day One.
So the one year premium of ₹1 lakh will remain the
same.  The premium increases in 2 years and 3 years' most
forward.   The
benefit also increases.  If you are
taking a policy of ₹1 lax for one year then you
get ₹12,000 maternity cost.  Meaning
you paid ₹1,000 as premium.  After 9 months
you can earn ₹12,000.  We will
also talk about what is covered in it.
And if you take it with Fast Forward, it
means you pay three years'
premium together which is ₹56,710
for a family of two.  I have taken 35 and 31 ages.  The
cover comes to ₹36,000.  ₹36,000
for 3 years cover.  A. You get your maternity benefit on
day one.  And the
premium to be paid for that is Rs 56710.  Now what we are
talking about here is it goes up to 75,000.
Depends on the sum.  Your maximum cover is Rs
25,000 per year and if you take fast forward
then a cover of Rs 75,000 is available
in maternity.  And
what is covered under maternity here?  Maternity covers
your delivery costs.  Whether it is normal,
caesarean, abortion, it
is also covered after the waiting period.  And along with that
IVF is covered, adoption is covered,
surrogacy is covered.  And new born
baby expenses are also covered up to the sum
assured.  This means that apart from the limit of Rs 12,000, Rs 36,000, Rs
75,000,
your newborn baby expenses over and above
are covered.  Whatever your sum assured is.  Whether it is Rs 10
lakh, Rs 20 lakh or Rs 50 lakh,
if the newborn baby is hospitalized up to that amount, the
full claim will be given.  After
delivery, by default newborn babies are
covered under this policy.  What
is not covered?  Vaccination is not covered.  And
antenatal expenses are also covered.
Meaning the mother has had any vaccinations before
delivery.  For the purpose of delivery.  If the mother has
any consultations or any tests that are
defined on that, those tests are also given,
so you can also allow those defined tests
up to whatever limit it is, whether it is ₹1000, 36000,
25000 or 75000, whatever plan you have chosen, you will
get it up to that limit. Remember there is a
waiting period of 9 months and the
policy has to be taken before conceiving, not after that.
Here in Neevapass, with and
without maternity premium is same because
maternity benefit is inbuilt.
I will show you with and without other plans, so that
you will get a comparison as to
how much cost we are paying for maternity.  So
in ICICI Low LAD Elevate if we
take it with maternity cover.  We took a policy of 10 lakhs
which also covered newborn baby expenses, maternity
and vaccination expenses
after a waiting period of 2 years.  So the
premium for one year is Rs 56890.
What is available in it?
You are getting delivery cost up to ₹1 lakh.  Meaning
10% of ₹1 lakh, maximum ₹1 lakh.  Newborn
baby expenses up to ₹2 lakh and vaccinations worth ₹10,000 are
available in this.  The premium being paid is Rs
56890 per year.  Now when will you get maternity
when you pay three premiums.
56890 now, then for next year,
after that you
can do maternity all.  Meaning, you understand 56890 * 3, now it
may increase according to age but also
according to inflation.  But you should understand that
roughly the premium you are paying is Rs
160-165 against which you will get a maternity benefit of Rs 1 lakh.  You will
get newborn baby expenses of Rs 2 lakh and
you can avail vaccinations worth up to Rs 10,000.
And if without maternity I
tell you the cost, what is the cost of this plan
for two people, 35 and 31 zone one premium
of 10 lakhs, that is 11373, which
means you can enjoy a premium cover of 10 lakhs for 11,000.
But the extra
cost that you are paying for every year is ₹400, that is
for maternity, more than ₹40,000 for
maternity benefit.  So if you feel
that you are getting this benefit against this premium
and it makes
financial sense for you, then you can take it.
Otherwise, maternity is often covered in your corporate policies
also.  So
now from there also you can see
what the limit is there.  Now let's talk about HDFC
Aggo Optima Secure because
different options are available here, plans of ₹0000, ₹
1 lakh, ₹150000 and ₹2 lakh
are available.  So I am
sharing all the premiums with you here.  ₹1
lakh in which parenthood rider is covered,
its premium for 50,000 is 35698,
for 1 lakh it is 48298 and for 2 lakh it is 70978,
this is one year premium, you will pay for 3 years,
after that you can take this benefit
₹500 for 1 lakh or ₹ lakh, so if we
talk about 500, it means you paid 335000
premium now, you will pay 35 next year or
whatever the premium will be according to the age and 35,
then you are paying approximately ₹10000
for cover of 500000, you are paying three
premiums after completion of 2 years
and if you do not take maternity benefit,
your premium for 10 lakh is 2186, in that
your insurance of 10 lakh
is covered.  Here, along with the insurance of Rs 10 lakh, you are
also getting Rs 50,000 maternity benefit and
here you are getting only parenthood rider.
So the premium of Rs 10 lakh without
parenthood rider of HDFC Arco is Rs 21806.
You will pay Rs 21,806 and can enjoy a cover of Rs 10 lakh.
And by paying additional premium, that is, by
paying ₹35,000, approximately ₹14,000 extra, you get an
insurance cover of ₹1 lakh
along with a ₹50,000 parenthood rider after a
waiting period of two years.  So
in the parenthood rider, the maternity cost which is your
delivery cost, whether it is normal, cesarean
, if you have IVF then complete parenthood will be
covered.  Newborn baby expenses
or vaccination expenses are not covered in HDFC.
So if you feel that by
adding so little maternity benefit, that is, by paying so much
premium, you are
not getting much additional maternity benefit, then you
can take a strong base cover.  You
can take a bigger health insurance cover
instead of going for a maternity cover.  So it
is completely your personal choice.  And we are available for one to
one consultation whether you should take it
or not.
You can contact our team
on the given number.  You can fill out a Google form.
Our team will connect with you and
provide you complete guidance.  And this is what I
wanted to tell you, what is the benefit of maternity benefit
?  What does it cost?  What
benefits are available and should I take it or not
?  We talked about that.  If you
found the video useful, please do
not forget to share it with your young friends who are still young and
want to see maternity cover
in policies.  And before we go, a quick reminder, if
you haven't subscribed to our channel yet, please do so.
So that you get the right
infection at the right time.  Thank you so much.
Stay safe, take care.
[Music]
Om